Guide to the Stanford Center for the Study of Families, Children, and Youth Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford Center for the Study of Families, Children, and Youth records
1972-1994
SC0482
Stanford Center for the Study of Families, Children, and Youth
5 Linear feet
Records pertaining to the administration of the center and its programs.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1994.
Information about Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Biography / Administrative History
The Stanford Center for the Study of Families, Children and Youth was established in 1974 with support from Father Flanagan's Boys' Town. The Center, known then as the Boys' Town Center for the Study of Youth Development at Stanford, sponsored interdisciplinary research on the effects of deprivation and neglect on the life chances of children. Professor Robert Sears was appointed interim Director during the organization of the Center, with Professor Al Hastorf appointed its first Director. Subsequent directors included Merrill Carlsmith, Michael Wald, and Sanford Dornbusch.
After the contract with Boys' Town was dissolved in 1986, the Center changed its name to the Stanford Center for the Study of Families, Children and Youth and broadened its focus from children aged 7 to 19 to encompass families and childhood concerns. Topics researched by its members have included the impact of daycare on a child's social development, effects of divorce and custody arrangements, how family variables affect school performance, minorities in the schools, and homelessness. Due to funding difficulties, the Center was dissolved in June 1994.
Scope and Content of Collection
These records, dating from 1972 to 1994, pertain largely to the administration of the Center and include correspondence of the Directors, contracts and legal records from the agreement with Boys' Town, annual reports, financial records, sponsored project files, and miscellaneous records.
Directors Albert Hastorf, 1975-80, and J. Merrill Carlsmith, 1980-84, are most heavily represented in the correspondence files. There are significantly fewer files for directors Michael Wald, 1985, Sanford Dornbusch, 1987-88, Shirley Feldman, 1993, and Susan Nolen-Hoeksema, 1994.
Projects headed by Sanford Dornbusch that are included in the sponsored project files include "Education for Parenting," "Homeless Families, Children and Youth," "Family and Peer Influences on High School Performance," and "Barriers to Hispanic Participation and Performance in High School Mathematics and Science Courses." Eleanor Maccoby's projects include "Adolescent Children of Recently Divorced Families" and "Child Custody: Contact, Conflict and Continutity." Shirley Feldman's projects include "Family Influences on Health" and "Normal Adolescent Development."
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following manner: Directors' correspondence - Box 1 through Box 5, folder 28 Contract files - Box 5, folder 29, through Box 6 Miscellaneous records - Box 7, folder 1 through folder 8 Annual reports and financial records - Box 7, folder 9 through Box 8 Sponsored project files - Box 9 and 10
Access Terms
Boys Town Center for the Study of Youth Development.; Boys Town Center.; Carlsmith, J. Merrill, 1936-; Dornbusch, Sanford M.; Feldman, S. Shirley.; Hastorf, Albert H., 1920-; Leiderman, P. Herbert; Maccoby, Eleanor E., 1917-; Child development.; Divorce.; Family.; Homelessness--California.; Mexican Americans--Education.; Parenting.
Collection Contents
- Director's Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Hastorf, Albert - personal correspondence (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Hastorf, Albert - chron file (includes invitations), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - A, 1976-80 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- American Studies Policy Committee [notice of meeting only], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - B, 3/11/77 - 5/2/80 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - B, 12/1/75 - 10/19/77 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Baltes, Paul, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Baron, Reuben M., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Bronfenbrenner - Regional Seminar, 12/8/78 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Bush Foundation (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - C, 1976-80 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Califano, Joseph A., 1976-77 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Cantril, Hadley, Memorial Fund, 1975-79 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Case Western Reserve University, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Cate School, 1976-77 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Chandler Chair Search, 1977-78 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Coladarci - Spencer Committee, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - D, 1976-80 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Dinkelspiel - Gores Awards (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - E, 1976-80 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - F, 1975-80 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Feldman, Ronald A., 1975-78 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Far West Laboratory, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - G, 1976-80 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Garden, Bruce (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Greenwald, Anthony, 1977-78 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - H, 1976-80 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Homewood Terrace (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - I, 1977-79 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- IBM, 1975-76 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - J, 1978-80 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - K, 1976-80 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - L, 3/5/79 - 7/28/80 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - L, 2/12/76 - 3/16/79 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Land, Edwin H., re University fund raising (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Leavitt, Harold, project (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Lilly Endowment (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Lindzey, Gardner - Physical handicap/deviance research idea, 1978-79 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Lumsden, Keith, project, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - M, 1976-80 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- MacArthur Foundation (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Maccoby, Eleanor (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Miller, William F. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Monteleone (Hotel) (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - N, 1977-80 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- NIH Guidelines for Human Subject Research (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Northrup Corporation (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - O, 1974-80 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- O'Connor, James P., 2/, 19/76 - 6/5/78 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - P, 1976-80 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - Q, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - R, 1979-80 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - R, 1975-78 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - S, 1979-80 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - S, 1975-78 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- San Jose Police Dept.: Child Abuse, Jay Houston and Marvin Lewis, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- San Mateo Foundation (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Schneider, David, Journal of Personality and Social Cognition (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Sherwin-Williams Management Development Seminar, 4/25/79 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Samenow, Stanton E., 1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Swinyard, Chester (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - T, 1976-79 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - U, 1977-80 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - V, 1977-80 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Van Hagen, John, 1976-77 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence -, 1976-80 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Wallace Village for Children, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Weir, Morton, 1979-80 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Wilbur, Curtis S., 1976-77 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Hastorf, Albert, correspondence - X,Y,Z, 1976-80 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - A, 1980-84 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - B, 1980-83 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - C, 1981-83 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Carnegie Foundation, 1981-84 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - D, 1981-83 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - E, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - F, 1981-83 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Fixsen, Dean, 1982-84 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - G, 1981-83 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Gibbs, Jack, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - H, 1980-83 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Hewlett Foundation, 1981-82 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - I, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - J, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Journal of Personality and Social Psychology review, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Robert Wood Johnson Foundation site visit, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - K, 1981-84 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - L, 1980-83 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - M, 1980-83 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - N, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - O, 1980-83 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Omaha, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - P, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - R, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Recommendations, 1982-83 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - S, 1980-83 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Spencer Foundation, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - T, 1980-83 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - V, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - W, 1980-83 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Carlsmith, J. Merrill, correspondence - X,Y,Z, 1981-82 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Wald, Michael, director, memoranda and proposal, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Dornbusch, Sanford, director, memoranda re appointment, 1987-88 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Feldman, Shirley, director, memoranda and correspondence, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Nolen-Hoeksema, Susan, director, memorandum re appointment, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Memos to members re affiliation with Children's Health Council, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Children's Health Council, initial funding correspondence, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Children's Health Council proposal, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Recommendation to the Board of Directors Committee of Boys Town on the Establishment of a Research and Training Complex, November 1972 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Agreement to Establish and Operate the Boys Town Center for the Study of Youth Development at the Catholic University of America, December 1973 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Agreement to Establish and Operate the Boys Town Center for the Study of Youth Development at Stanford University, March 1974 (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Boys Town Contract, January, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Boys Town settlement papers, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Boys Town settlement (legal documents), 1981-82 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Boys Town settlement (legal documents), 1981-82 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Boys Town settlement (legal documents and memos), 1981-82 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Lawsuit history (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Lawsuit history (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Lawsuit history (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Grand Scheme, the - memoranda on fundraising plan, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Public Policy Advisory Committee meeting, 4/24/89 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Visiting Committee, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- H&S Report - survey of institutes, labs and centers at Stanford (completed form on Youth Center), 1985 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Change in Center name, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Center memberships, 1986/87-1993/94 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Center publications (bibliography), 1989-90 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Center newsletter, 1987-90 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Articles on Center from Campus Report, Stanford Magazine, Stanford Observer (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Brochure, Directory of Members, circa 1986 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Annual Report, 1973/74 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Financial Report, 1973/74 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Annual Report, 1974/75 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Financial Report, 1974/75 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Budget correspondence, 1974/75 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Correspondence re directorship, 1974/75 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Annual Report, 1975/76 (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Financial Report, 1975/76 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Budget Correspondence, 1975/76 (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Annual Report, 1976/77 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Financial Report, 1976/77 (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Budget Correspondence, 1976/77 (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Annual Report, 1977/78 (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Financial Report, 1977/78 (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Budget Correspondence, 1977/78 (Box 7, Folder 25)
- Annual Report, 1978/79 (Box 7, Folder 26)
- Financial Report, 1978/79 (Box 7, Folder 27)
- Budget Correspondence, 1978/79 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Research funding records, 1978/79 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Annual Report, 1979/80 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Financial Report, 1979/80 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Budget Correspondence, 1979/80 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Academic year support, 1979/80 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Academic year funding, 1980/81 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Report to Omaha from, 3/1/81 - 9/1/81 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Report of Dornbusch's phone conversation, 4/2/81 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Boys Town audit, 3/1/81 - 8/31/81 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Annual Report, 1981/82 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Financial Report, 1/1/82 - 8/31/82 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Boys Town audit, Jan-Aug 1982 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Report to Boys Town, June 1, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Budget correspondence, 1980-82 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Annual Report, 1982/83 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Financial Report, 1982/83 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Funding, 1982/83 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Audit, 1982/83 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Annual Report, 1983/84 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Financial Report, 1983/84 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Audits, 1983/84 (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Annual Report, 1984/85 (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Financial Report, 1984/85 (Box 8, Folder 24)
- Annual Report, 1985/86 (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Financial Report, 1985/86 (Box 8, Folder 26)
- Research support grants, 1986/87 (Box 8, Folder 27)
- Financial Report, 1986/87 (Box 8, Folder 28)
- Budget, 1986/87 (Box 8, Folder 29)
- Budget report, 1987/88 (Box 8, Folder 30)
- Budget report, 1988/89 (Box 8, Folder 31)
- Budget, 1988/89 (Box 8, Folder 32)
- Budget notes, 1988/89 (Box 8, Folder 33)
- Grants and funding requests, 1989/90 (Box 8, Folder 34)
- Budget notes, 1989/90 (Box 8, Folder 35)
- Financial Report, 1990/91 (Box 8, Folder 36)
- Funding and grants, 1990/91 (Box 8, Folder 37)
- Operating budget, 1990/91 (Box 8, Folder 38)
- Funding and grants, 1991/92 (Box 8, Folder 39)
- Operating budget, 1991/92 (Box 8, Folder 40)
- Funding requests, 1992/93 (Box 8, Folder 41)
- Operating budget, 1992/93 (Box 8, Folder 42)
- Maccoby, "Adolescent Children of Recently Divorced Families" (Box 9)
- Carnegie Corporation, SPO 11613, final report, Dornbusch, "Education for Parenting", 1993 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Carnegie Corporation, Dornbusch, "Education for Parenting"SPO 11613, 10/1/92 - 6/30/93 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Johnson Foundation, SPO 90-45, final report, Dornbusch (financial statements), 1992 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- UCSF, SPO 10528, final report, Feldman, "Family Influences on Health", 9/92 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- UCSF, SPO 10528, questionnaires and misc. documents, Feldman, "Family Influences on Health", 9/92 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Dornbusch, "Homeless Families, Children and Youth," final report, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Johnson Foundation, SPO 7850, final report, Dornbusch, "Homeless Families, Children and Youth", 1992 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Johnson Foundation, SPO 10034, final report, Dornbusch, "Homeless Families, Children and Youth", 1992 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Johnson Foundation, SPO 10651, final report, Dornbusch, "Homeless Families, Children and Youth", 1992 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Koret Foundation, Grant # 91-0228, final report, Dornbusch, "Homeless Families, Children and Youth", 1992 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- United Way, SPO 10045, final report, Dornbusch, "Homeless Families, Children and Youth", 1992 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Hewlett Foundation, SPO 7679, final report, Dornbusch, "Homeless Families, Children and Youth", 1992 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Johnson Foundation, Dornbusch, "Homeless Families, Children and Youth", 1991 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Johnson Foundation, Dornbusch, "Homeless Families, Children and Youth", 1989-90 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Johnson Foundation, Dornbusch, "Homeless Families, Children and Youth", 1992 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Koret Foundation, Dornbusch, "Homeless Families, Children and Youth", 1991 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Grant Foundation, SPO 5459, Year 1 Reporting, Maccoby, "Adolescent Children of Recently Divorced Families", 1988-89 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Grant Foundation, SPO 5459, Year 2 Reporting, 1989-90 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Grant Foundation, SPO 5459, Year 3 Reporting, Maccoby, "Adolescent Children of Recently Divorced Families", 1990-91 (Box 9, Folder 19)
- Grant Foundation, SPO 5459, Year 4 Reporting, Maccoby, "Adolescent Children of Recently Divorced Families", 1991-92 (Box 9, Folder 20)
- Grant Foundation Maccoby, "Adolescent Children of Recently Divorced Families", (includes drafts of three chapters from proposed book), 7/1/91 - 6/30/92 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Grant Foundation, Year 4 Renewal, Maccoby (includes 2 papers from the research), "Adolescent Children of Recently Divorced Families", 1990-91 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Spencer Foundation, Reports, Dornbusch/Leiderman, "Family and Peer Influences on High School Performance", 1987-1991 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Spencer Foundation, Final Report, Dornbusch/Leiderman, "Family and Peer Influences on High School Performance", 1991 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Carnegie Corporation, Reporting, Elliott/Feldman, "Normal Adolescent Development", 11/87 - 8/89 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Carnegie Corporation, Reporting, Dornbusch/Leiderman, "Barriers to Hispanic Participation and Performance in High School Mathematics and Science Courses", 3/88 - 6/90 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Carnegie Corporation, Dornbusch/Leiderman, "Barriers to Hispanic Participation and Performance in High School Mathematics and Science Courses"Proposal, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Drown Foundation, Reporting, Dornbusch, work on minorities and education, July 1989 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- NIH, SPO 162L060, financial reports, Maccoby/Mnookin, "Child Custody: Contact, Conflict and Continuity", 1985-89 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- NIH, SPO 162L060, Year 2 Renewal, Maccoby/Mnookin, "Child Custody: Contact, Conflict and Continuity", 1983-85 (Box 10, Folder 10)